# **ASAD ZIA IQBAL**

House B-I-347, Kurri Road, Muslim Town, Sadiqabad, Rawalpindi Tel: Res +92 (51) 4345786 Cell: +92 (333) 5151321

Email: <u>asadziaiqbal@hotmail.com</u> **Skype:** asadziaiqbal

### **Technical Expertise**

Focus Area: <u>Institutional Development, Capacity Building, Monitoring and Evaluation,</u>
<u>Governance, Project Management, Training and Development,</u>

**Experience:** More than 12 years of experience in the development sector. Strong cross-cultural communication, problem-solving skills and sensitivity to gender issues. Experience in report writing, monitoring and evaluation, presentations and budget management. Ability to work with a wide cross-section of partners: Government, NGOs, communities, and international donors and can work under pressure, solid computer skills and able to work in multi-cultural environment.

### **Professional Experience**

Programme Manager – Capacity Building
Assessment and Strengthening Programme (USAID)

April 2012 to date

### Main Responsibilities

- Developing capacity assessment tool, conducting assessment and building the capacity of USAID funded organizations, thereof, in order to make sure that institutions are accountable, transparent, efficient and effective in their service delivery.
- Preparing Capacity Building Plans (CBPs) for CSOs based on capacity assessments.
- Develoing Strategic and Capacity Building Plans for various Punjab, KP and Sindh local government institutions and Civil Society Organizations.
- Conceptualising and developing various products and services for the CSOs in key functional areas of Governance, Financial Management, Procurement Management, Human Resource Management, Project Management, Information Technology and Monitoring and Evaluation.
- Intensive interaction and coordination with provincial and federal government officials and elected and non-elected local government functionaries.

### Task accomplished at ASP

- a. Baseline study Institutional Capacity of Civil Society Organisation in Pakistan.
- Conceptualised, developed and conducted research study on determining baseline for capacity building initiatives for CSOs.
- Developed questionnaire covering all functional areas i.e. governance, financial management, human resource management, procurement, program delivery and monitoring and evaluation.
- Data collected using online tool (<u>www.surveymonkey.com</u>) and Focus Group Discussions/interviews of selected beneficiaries to validate the data.
- Analysis of data for key findings and report writing

### b. Policy and Procedure Manuals

- Developed policy and procedure manuals in Financial Management, Human Resource Management, Procurement Management, Monitoring and Evaluation, and Information Technology
- Further customised these manuals for USAID grantee organisations after carefully reviewing their existing systems and procedures

### c. Capacity Assessment of CSOs

- Developed Capacity Assessment tool for CSOs in each functional areas.
- Conducted assessment of CSOs highlighting high to moderate risk areas for capacity development.
- Developed Capacity Building Plans for CSOs.
- Provided hands-on training, coaching and mentoring to CSOs along with policy manuals, tools and templates for system development.

### d. ASP learning portal (www.asp-aid.org)

 Developed and implemented an integrated ASP learning portal that includes Organisation Capacity Assessment Tool (OCAT), Discussion Forums, Ask an Expert, Video Tutorials, E-learning and Webinars.

### e. Enterprise Resource Planning software for CSOs

- Lead the team of two consultants for customising **Enterprise Resource Planning** software using OpenERP platform. The software has been developed for CSOs that help them to manage their Financial Management, Human Resource Management and Project Management.
- Provided training to over 45 organisations on ERP.
- Successfully deployed ERP in over 10 organisations.

### f. Webinars

• Planned and conducted webinars on different topics on Governance, Financial Administration, Human Resource Management, Procurement Management, Information Technology and Monitoring and Evaluation.

## g. Monitoring and Evaluation

- Reviewed and further improved the Performance Management Plan (PMP) of the Assessment and Strengthening Program
- Prepared M&E plan for Municipal Services Program Government of Khyber Pakhtoonkhwa, Pakistan.
- Implemented monitoring plan of all project and task enlisted above
- Conducted interviews for various positions in M&E for public sector entities i.e. Municipal Services Program (MSP), KP.

Team Lead, Certification
Pakistan Centre for Philanthropy
July 2011 to March 2012

Prepared revised 5 year strategic planning (2013 – 2017) for PCP. The process includes
developing strategic framework for PCP, internal and external environment scan using

questionnaire, stakeholder's interviews and focus group discussions with clients/beneficiaries (Certified CSOs).

- Developed operational plans based on the strategic planning document.
- Planning, coordinating and monitoring of the certification process.
- Assuring quality of the certification process, highlighting any deficiencies therein and suggesting ways and means to rectify them.
- On-job training of desk reviewers and field evaluators.
- Identifying and rectifying any deficiencies on part of Programme Officers regarding desk review and preparations for field review in any given case.
- Ensuring that the evaluation report furnished by the Programme Officers is complete in all
  respects, and that all aspects of the case have been properly dealt with by highlighting both
  merits and demerits thereof.
- Carrying out field inspections and monitoring of field evaluators.
- Submitting a periodic report to the Executive Director regarding the general quality of evaluation conducted and suggesting measures to address the lacunas, if any.
- Briefing the Executive Director about all cases that are to be presented to the Certification Panel at least one week before the meeting.
- Presenting the cases before the Certification Panel along with the Senior Programme Manager and addressing the members' inquiries, concerns and observations about each case.
- Ensuring that all NPO certification orientation sessions for Government, Donors (International and National) and NPOs are conducted effectively.
- Giving advice and policy input to the Executive Director on programme development particularly certification portfolio.
- Preparing analytical write ups; developing policy papers, periodic progress reports for internal and external consumption, writing concept notes, preparing promotional material & brochures, annual reports, and making presentations on various prestigious fora.
- Maintaining effective liaison with concerned agencies and government departments on behalf of the Certification Unit.
- Assessing the performance of the certification unit members on an annual basis.

### Task accomplished at PCP

#### a) CSOs evaluation

 Evaluated over 300 organisations including thematic areas such as Education, Agriculture, Water and Sanitation, Micro Credit, Environment and Health (Reproductive Health, Treatment and Prevention of Blindness, Prevention and Control of HIV/AIDS, Treatment of Kidney related diseases, Tuberculosis and Leprosy).

## Programme Officer, Certification Unit Pakistan Centre for Philanthropy (PCP) April 2006 to July 2011

- Conducting evaluation of Civil Society Organisations applying for certification.
- Preparing analytical write ups; developing evaluation reports, preparing agenda for certification panel meeting ensuring that reports are consistent with the report requirements, and maintaining the records of all panel meetings.

- Maintaining effective liaison with concerned agencies and government departments on behalf of the Certification Unit.
- Analyzing financial reports and in-line with CSOs budget utilization.
- Providing technical assistance to the CSOs on financial, programmatic and governance's issues.
- Preparing annual, quarterly, monthly and weekly work plans.
- Managing and implementing "Institutional Development of PCP" project funded by the World Bank.

### Monitoring and Evaluation Officer, Asian Development Bank (ADB), Islamabad Feb 2005 to April 2006

- Determining systematically and objectively as possible the relevance, effectiveness, efficiency, sustainability and impact of activities in light of specified objectives of the programmes/ projects of an organization.
- Evaluated 70+ organizations throughout Pakistan including major and bigger organizations like FPAP, SKMT, Sahara for Life Trust, SMB, PEC, etc.
- Written, as part of the certification team, reports on the critical evaluations of the evaluated organization.
- Provide technical input on the issues regarding governance (under laws governing NPOs in Pakistan), financial management and programme delivery.
- Financial analyses of organization on the basis of its sustainability, cash flows, liquidity etc.

## Junior Programme Officer, Pakistan Centre for Philanthropy (PCP) March 2003 to Jan 2005

- Assisting senior program manager in developing program feasibility report and certification model for NPOs,
- Coordinating with NPOs, Government entities, and other stakeholders for consultations and pilot testing of the certification model,
- conducting desk review of organisation based on the documents provided,
- preparing results matrix of findings of desk review for field verification,
- field verification of the findings and inspection of program sites, governing maters, financial undertakings and personnel related matters for final evaluation report.

### Task accomplished:

- a. Certification feasibility
- b. Certification model for CSOs
- c. Certification manual containing SOPs and workflows
- d. Pilot testing of certification model

Assistant Program Coordinator (Project Officer)
Pakistan Foundation Fighting Blindness (PFFB), Islamabad
Feb 2001 to June 2001

- monitor, assign work orders, supervising the work of duplication department, labelling and distribution department,
- distribution of audio cassettes to blinds,
- abridgement of books, recording, policy planning of the project, stocktaking and procurement of cassettes.

#### **PAPERS AND REPORTS**

2012

Written "Programme Performance Evaluation Reports" of NPO after rigorous, thorough and detailed field evaluation of over 300 organisations

2011

Prepared project proposal, developed M&E frameworks, procedures and policies, financial management policies for various CSOs as freelance consultant

Prepared three 5-year project proposal for seeking funding for certification and capacity development of the CSOs

Edited the profiles for directory of certified organisations "Gateway to Giving"

To become Certification Model a living document, taken a lead role in 3<sup>rd</sup> standards revision

2010

Written various *concept papers* on different issues including papers for CBR to streamline and strengthen existing tax regime applicable on NPOs in Pakistan.

2007 Plan, coordinated and conducted a study on *the Government-CSO collaboration in Pakistan*.

Actively involved in development of *Operational Policy for Education (PPP)* and *District Education Manuals* for Punjab

2005 Research Report on "Corporate Philanthropy – a case of public listed companies 2000-2004" and two seminal studies in 2006 and 2007 During this assignment, following functions were performed:

- Supervise a team of 4 for data collection from (Company Registration Offices – CROs, Karachi Stock Exchange –KSE and Securities and Exchange Commission of Pakistan – SECP
- Data analysis
- · Analytical input in report

### 2003 PCP Transcriptions

Transcribed various consultations of PCP officials with Donors, Stakeholders, NGOs and Government during Enabling Environment Initiative – (EEI) Project.

## **Experience Sharing with International Partners**

#### Cambodia:

To dialogue and establish a regional learning platform on CSO accountability and Good Governance for Asia region, Phnom Penh. During the conference, presented PCP's certification system and drafted a mechanism for institutionalising learning platform for CSOs.

#### India:

To share and learn from each others experiences in Not-for-Profit sector, India. During the visit meetings were held with (i) Credibility Alliance India; to share and learn from each others experiences in NPO certification/ accreditation (ii) Charities Aid Foundation India; to learn about their facilitation role and support services viz charity/philanthropy promotion in India (iii) Indian Centre for Philanthropy and Centre for Advancement of Philanthropy India; to learn about their philanthropy promotion and research programmes and draw some mutually beneficial lessons to improve the working and approach of PCP in regional context (iv) meetings with the relevant Indian government officers; to help develop understanding of the legal, regulatory and fiscal environment in India viz nonprofits which can give an insight to the team to draw some positive lessons to be replicated in Pakistan for the non-profit sector.

#### Thailand:

Attended conference on developing "Financial Accounting Standards for Non-Profit Organizations in South Asia" in Bankok, Thiland The conference was arranged by Asian Philanthropic Consortium (APPC) in Bangkok, Thailand to draft Financial Accounting Standards for NPOs in South Asian region. Eight countries, Pakistan, India, Hong Kong, Philippine, China, Bangladesh, Thailand and Sri-Lanka discussed their reporting procedures.

#### Education

2009 – 2011	Masters in Business Administration (Finance) Bahria University, Islamabad
1998 – 2002	CMA – Part completed Institute of Cost and Management Accountants, Islamabad
1995 – 1997	Bachelors of Commerce (B.Com) University of the Punjab, Lahore

### **Training Courses/ Workshops**

- Training course on Project Management organised by Lahore University of Management Sciences (LUMS), Lahore in 2013.
- Training course on Monitoring and Evaluation organised by Lahore University of Management Sciences (LUMS), Karachi in 2012.
- Training course on Advance Excel and PowerPoint (2007) organised by Management Development Institute (MDI), Islamabad in 2009.
- Training course on Change Management, Marketing and Advocacy and Persuasive Report Writing organised by Management Development Institute (MDI), Islamabad in 2009.
- Training course on Participatory Planning, Monitoring and Evaluation organised by Human Resource Development Institute (HRDI), Islamabad.

### Skills

- Excellent program/ project management, monitoring and evaluation skills and using project management software.
- Good training skills
- Excellent computing skills using MS-Office (MS Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Access, etc.),
   MS-Project 2007 (server environment), SPSS etc and various open-source or free-online portals such as Google (forms, spreadsheets and databases).
- Effective writing and communication skills

### Membership

Member of the "Project Management Institute, USA", since 2007

## Languages

- English, good written, spoken and comprehension skills
- Urdu, good written, spoken and comprehension skills
- Punjabi, spoken skills only